I hear you love walk and talks.
Yes, because we sit too much. Yeah.
And also our company is just next
to this park, so it's great.
Is it all AI talk all the time here?
I don't know other people's talk,
but I talk AI all the time.
But that's the only thing I know.
Fei-Fei Li is a giant in
the field of computer vision,
a branch of AI dedicated to
teaching machines to see.
She made a breakthrough with
ImageNet, a visual library
that sparked the modern AI revolution,
earning her the title, 'Godmother of AI'.
And she's been a pioneer
at AI's center ever since,
as a Stanford professor, a
Google executive, an advisor
to US presidents, and
a relentless advocate
for AI that serves people.
I feel the leaders
of AI are not talking enough
about empowering humanity.
They're talking too much
about replacing humanity,
replacing jobs.
Now she's adding startup
co-founder to her star resume.
What's it like running your own shop? I
feel like a tiger mom.
While the rest of the AI
world doubles down on large
language models like ChatGPT
and Claude, Li is betting on
a new frontier, world models.
She's building AI that aims to predict
what happens next in the real world,
not just the next word in a sentence.
So what can world models do ultimately
that LLMs will never be able to?
Can words put down fires?
Can words cook an omelet?
Li and her startup, World Labs,
is competing in a crowded field of rivals,
all making the same bet
that world models are
the next big leap in AI.
Did you ever imagine AI would be this big?
Have I imagined the
entire civilization is going
to be redefined by AI?
The cultural shifts, the
geopolitical landscape?
I would not have imagined that.
Before she became a
leading AI scientist,
Li was just a curious
kid looking at the world.
What was young Fei-Fei like as a kid?
It was '80s and '90s in
China. My city was Chengdu.
My dad is quite a curious
soul about nature,
so I got quite a dosage
of chasing after bugs and,
and running after puppies
and going to the mountains to, to draw
and sketch with my dad.
And, you know, reading.
Cutting your hair short,
loving aerospace and physics.
Did you see yourself as a rebel?
As a kid, right? You're preteen.
You almost have to be a rebel just
because you want to make
a statement for yourself.
But the love of nature and science
and physics, the love of aerospace
and outer space, those are
part of my identity. You
emigrated from China to the US in - New
Jersey. In the 90s.
Yeah. What was it like coming here
as a teenager back then?
That was tough. Shifting
the whole thing, culture,
language, life
as a teenager is perhaps
one of the hardest times
because you're finding who you are
and then suddenly you don't
even know the world, right?
Li learned English,
finished high school,
studied physics at Princeton
while running the family dry
cleaning business on weekends,
and followed her dreams to
Caltech, where she earned her PhD
and became a computer scientist.
You've been studying artificial
intelligence since then.
It was super niche. Yes.
What
was the field like back then?
That was a beautiful period.
It was really pure curiosity
because there was no
money, there was no power,
there was no fanfare, there was no hype.
We were there just the same
as scientists look into the
sky, go down in the ocean.
I was deeply curious.
How does AI see
and how is it different
from how you or I see?
We use our eyes to
drive the sensory system
to turn that into signals in the brain,
and the brain does computing.
It's not that different for computers.
We need to learn the pattern of the world
and understand objects,
colors, environments.
A lot of seeing is
preparing humans to act.
You wake up this morning,
you hug your kids,
you go downstairs, prepare
some breakfast, grab your key,
drive to your work.
Everything I've described
so far, you've done that
with your spatial intelligence. So
it's got to be hard to
get computers to do that.
Yes.
Li was working on this back in 2006.
She built ImageNet, a massive catalog
of 14 million pictures in
over 21,000 categories,
the largest assembled at that time,
because Li saw that algorithms
needed data to get smarter.
So what was the spark for ImageNet?
Nobody was paying attention to data.
My students and I had that
epiphany that learning needs
to be driven by data.
In 2010, Li turned
ImageNet into a competition.
Who could build the best algorithm
to correctly identify the most images?
In 2012, Geoffrey Hinton's
University of Toronto team entered
with AlexNet, an algorithm
powered by NVIDIA Graphics cards.
The result marked a turning point.
That combination, massive
amount of data, neural networks,
and GPU computing power
became the golden recipe
for modern AI and cemented Li's legacy.
What do you feel when you look at this?
It's not the eight of us.
It's the entire humanity.
That's really the main story here.
Because this comes from
the photo of, what,
about a hundred years ago when
industrialization was in the
booming phase and big urban
skylines are being built.
That was a civilizational moment.
It's amazing that you're
being recognized here,
but like, could they
have centered the photo?
Come on. It's true because
there's more space here.
I asked you about being the godmother
of AI a few years ago. You
did. How
do you feel about that title?
You know, Emily,
I would never call myself
godmother of anything.
Remember, Emily, when you
asked me, I was like, oh.
I was taken aback
because I don't naturally
think about myself
as godmother of anything.
That's not my personality.
I focus on work.
If I rejected that on
that spot, we once again
would be in a situation
where women just don't get
recognized the same way as men.
I want more women to be
called godmother of whatever
creation, innovation,
discovery that they have done.
So do you embrace the term now or?
Embrace is a big word.
I don't go around and
say, "Hi, I'm Fei-Fei
I'm the godmother of AI."
But people have adopted
that term thanks to you.
Artificial intelligence had
long been discussed in policy
and tech circles as something perpetually
right around the corner.
Until ChatGPT, AI went
from a niche research field
to the most talked about
technology on the planet.
Large language models, image
generators, video generators.
Suddenly it seemed like everyone was
or wanted to be in the AI business.
And let's be honest, things
have come pretty far.
Li saw an opportunity and
launched her own startup in 2024.
What's it like running your own shop?
So here's the thing. I'm
by far the most senior in the company.
From my co-founders to my
engineers and researchers
and scientists, they're so
talented, but they're also young.
I do feel like a mom.
And oftentimes I feel like a tiger mom.
I do run this shop as, I
would say, high standard.
Li is working on
advancing world models.
If ImageNet taught AI how
to see, this technology aims
to guide AI through the physical world
because describing how to catch a ball
and actually catching one
are very different things.
And super intelligence,
she's betting that lies
beyond chatbots.
The rest of the AI industry
is focusing on LLMs.
What can't LLMs do?
If we want to create a
world where we continue
to push scientific discovery,
where we want machines like
robots to be a partner to us,
all this language cannot do it alone.
Building world model
and spatial intelligence
is not about anti - LLM.
It's about the next frontier
and the next chapter.
So what exactly is a world model? World
model at this point
is an overloaded term.
We look at spatial intelligence
as three different kind of functions.
One is rendering, one is simulation,
and the third one is planning.
Rendering is the world model outputs
beautiful pixels for humans to consume.
Most likely you're thinking
about [OpenAI's] Sora.
The second class of world
model is they do simulation,
but it doesn't serve just humans.
It serves machines.
They are focused on capturing
the actual structure
of the world, the geometry
structure based on physics.
The third kind of world model
planning helps you to know
what is the next thing you need to do.
For example, if you have
a cup, a world model
that serves as a planner will
let the robot know, pick it up
and put it somewhere else.
And that is a world model
that is very closely coupled
with robotics.
Marble is World Lab's first step towards
creating a world model.
It's a platform that lets
anyone generate an explorable,
editable 3D world from a
single visual or text prompt.
Now, this is a showcase page
of some user-generated world.
You can see they created
a room, a beautiful room.
Now you look at this,
you're like, Fei-Fei,
this is no different from a picture.
But here's the thing.
It actually is a world
because I can navigate in it.
So like a game, I can move
forward. I can turn around.
I can go anywhere.
Here, it's a fully consistent 3D world.
So who or what companies are using
Marbel right now?
Why is Marble useful? For
example, virtual production.
In movies, people are using Marble
because they can shoot
actors in any environment.
Game developers.
Marble has completely lowered
the amount of resource
and time one needs.
We also have robotics example.
This is a collaboration with NVIDIA where
they're using Marble environments
to augment the training of robots.
What are you training these models on
that others don't have?
We are training these
models on two things, right?
One is specially prepared data.
Pixel data are more nuanced than
language data in the sense that
there's more information in a picture.
There's camera information.
Another one is algorithmic
and architectural innovation
because no one has created
generative world models as we
have in terms of creating 3D
and eventually 4D worlds. So would
you say that's the secret?
Yeah, I guess so.
Well, the real secrets are
people, as I always say.
But yes, the data and the algorithm
and the, the system we have built.
You've raised a billion dollars.
How is the business doing? The
business is still early.
This phase of World Labs,
we're focusing on building the technology.
Building the technology
isn't the only part of the job.
When Li isn't heads down at World Labs,
she's out making the case
for the next frontier of AI.
Absolutely.
Please welcome to the stage.
Fei-Fei Li, co-founder
and CEO at World Labs for a conversation
with Bloomberg's Emily Chang. All
of this rolls up into
robotics, so I, I want
to get your take on the field.
And humanoids in particular.
Funding for humanoids hit $6 billion,
but you know, they still can't load my
dishwasher as fast as I can.
They still can't go
get my Amazon packages.
Will world models,
world labs close the gap
between hype and reality? That's
a loaded question, Emily.
First of all, first of all,
robotics is going to be one
of the most important revolution
in human industrialization.
$6 billion is too small, right?
If you look at self-driving
cars investment,
if you look at language models investment,
it took way more than $6 billion.
Are we going to close the gap?
I do believe World Labs is working on one
of the most critical technology in the
spatial physical intelligence.
And obviously that's
the, that's the hope. But
Li isn't alone.
World models are the tech
industry's latest obsession
with startups and tech giants alike all
sprinting to build them.
For anything from design to
self-driving cars, robots
and factories, to eventually machines
that can navigate the
unpredictable reality
of the human home.
You're competing against big
players with deep pockets.
How worried are you about that? As
an entrepreneur and a co-founder, CEO,
I'm paranoid every day.
I don't think there's a moment
I would say, "Hey, I feel
so relaxed." You know?
So yes, I am worried, but am
I paralyzed? Absolutely not.
We have an incredible team.
We also have the focus.
You know, a lot of big
companies, they have
a lot on the, on the table.
We have one thing on the table,
and we're focusing on that thing. Emily,
Nice to meet you.
The war for talent is so fierce.
Why work with Fei-Fei
when there are so many
powerful AI companies out there? Well,
I started working with Fei-Fei
way before it was cool in
2012. Yeah, I did my PhD
with Fei-Fei at Stanford
way back in the day.
You can go to a lot of big tech,
but your hands can't change
that trajectory in, in many instances.
Here,
we're 50 people.
Your hands can change the
trajectory of this company.
That's a beautiful thing
to have in your life.
World Labs may be a small team,
but the investment in
world models is gigantic.
$3 billion and growing.
Still, it's early days.
The field hasn't even agreed
on how to build them yet.
Would you say it's like 2019 for chatbots
where everyone was chasing LLMs
and trying to make it happen,
but they hadn't cracked the code yet?
Is that where we are for world models?
Yeah, that's probably a
fair description. We're early.
We're a lot earlier compared to LLMs. But
Will there be some sort of explosion
and aha moment where we're like,
"Oh, now we understand." If
we do it right, yes.
That's the magic of
technology and science.
When it hits that milestone,
it becomes magical. There
are skeptics in the AI
and robotics world that say,
"This isn't the next breakthrough.
It's just the next hype cycle."
What do you say to that?
I think even a good
science can be hyped.
I believe spatial intelligence
and physical intelligence are fundamental
to machine intelligence.
And these are the frontier questions
that I believe firmly in as a
scientist, as a technologist,
and also as an entrepreneur.
I believe they will provide incredible
market value. Building
wrld models is incredibly
resource intensive.
Do you need more power? Do you
need more capital to get to
where you want to be? That
we don't know yet.
We're too early. We're
likely to need more power
and more resources.
And can you get that?
I don't know.
We have to do a good job to, to earn it.
Getting world models out
of the demo phase will
take more time and money.
Meanwhile, investment in
generative AI has soared,
and Americans have
strong feelings about it.
I'm sure you've seen the
video of former Google CEO,
Eric Schmidt, getting booed
at a college graduation.
So today we stand on this edge
of another technological transformation.
You spend a lot of time with
students. What are they saying?
And if they're scared, are
the fears justified? Yeah,
I do spend a lot of time with students.
Even Stanford students reflect
some of this mixed sentiment.
There is anxiety. There is sense of hope.
There is also excitement.
There is also confusion.
There is also simultaneously
a sense of dignity
and agency when AI can help me do things
that I couldn't do before.
And a sense of loss of dignity
and agency if AI is going to take my job.
AI
Has
Got to go.
So what happens if the US
loses faith in this technology
while the rest of the world races ahead?
US is such an important
country in terms of its impact
to the world that if we are not showing a
positive attitude
and positive path towards
AI, everybody loses.
And I don't wish for that
because US has been a thought
leader in the world when it
comes to technology and
science and economy.
And if we can show that we can
create incredible technology
and incredible economic value using AI
and have a positive cultural impact,
the world will see it as a role model. Li
knows a thing or two
about AI and its impact.
Over her career, she took
roles at big tech companies,
venture capital firms,
co-founded an AI institute at Stanford,
and advised US presidents
and the United Nations on AI policy.
There's nothing artificial
about artificial intelligence.
It's inspired by people.
It's created by people.
And most importantly, it
has an impact on people.
You've advised President
Biden, President Trump, the UN
on technology and AI policy.
How do you approach conversations
with world leaders? I
don't go in hyping.
I don't go in providing extreme rhetoric.
Either it's total utopia
or total doomsday.
It's very important that
whoever I talk to knows
that I'm a scientist.
What do they need? They
need scientific facts,
but I think it's important
to be at their service
and to speak my mind, to
push back if they're wrong,
because that's my responsibility.
And have they been wrong?
Oh, yes, for sure.
We all have been wrong. This
technology moves so fast.
I don't blame them. Most
of our policymakers don't come from
computer science background. What
is the role of regulation?
What should that look like?
First and foremost, root
that in science, not science fiction.
A lot of the AI policy world conversation
with people from Silicon Valley
talk about the extinction
of humanity, the, the,
the AGI machine overlord
that distracts the real policy work.
The second recommendation is
ensure a healthy ecosystem,
resource the public sector,
resource STEM education in K-12 or K-16.
Human capital at the end
of the day is the most
important resource of our world.
And we want a thriving society of people,
not a thriving society
of just machines. What
do you worry could go
wrong with world models?
Like if we're giving
people even more realistic
and more powerful AI, does
that create even more opportunities
for really bad things to happen?
World models, language models,
these are powerful models
that can create mis and disinformation.
Empowered robots can be
weaponized by bad actors
and students who
are not properly motivated
can use technology
as a lazy crutch instead of
a empowering learning tool.
I, I worry about that a lot.
So I think a lot of things can go wrong
with technology, not just AI.
It could have gone wrong with
electricity, with cars, with,
you know, PC, with internet. Some
of the most powerful CEOs
in AI right now have been
accused of having God complexes
because they seem to think they know
what's best for humanity.
What do you think of that term? I
think it's dangerous for any individual
to think they know better
than everybody else.
As a CEO, as an entrepreneur,
our founding premise is
we are here to contribute to the society
and to empower people.
It's not our position
to make every single
decision for people. But
isn't that the path we're on?
I mean, these are really
powerful people.
I think it's too early to tell
Emily. I'm not being naive.
I know what you're talking
about. I also have my concern.
I don't think having God
complex is constructive,
and I wouldn't want to do that myself,
but we have a democratic society.
This is another reason I
think our civil society should
not give up on AI.
We need the voices. We need
the collective governance.
But let's now throw the
baby with the bathwater.
The governance shouldn't
be, let's stop AI,
because this is a technology
that can discover cure for
diseases, can empower students
and teachers, can help our elderly.
So that's the baby here.
But right now, we are
in a very messy period.
This is also why I feel
personal responsibility
to speak the truth I believe in
as a scientist and an educator.
Li has spent her life
teaching machines to see.
She gave AI its eyes.
Now in her second act, she's trying
to give it a world to live in.
As the scientist who helped
spark the modern AI revolution,
perhaps we shouldn't put it past her.
Where is this all going? Where
are we in five years? This
This is where I reveal I'm an optimist.
The, the arc of history
is long. I paraphrase Dr.
King. I believe it bends
towards benevolence.
Now, we're not a perfect world of people
and community, but 2026
today is better than
2026 BC for the majority
of the population.
And I think it's because despite
all of our dark underbelly,
we have it in our DNA.
We want our offsprings
to live a better life,
and we have moral compasses collectively
to move the society towards benevolence.
My hope is in humanity.
Is it true you're
obsessed with UFOs? When I
was a kid. Like,
Have you read the documents
they're declassifying?
No.
I think it's part of
that dreamy curiosity
as a kid is what's out there. Do
you think there's aliens out there? So
as a physics student,
you learn Drake's equation.
Drake's equation computes
the probability of potential
of outer space aliens.
So there is a potential number. Wow.
Okay. Favorite sci-fi movie?
Contact. By far my
favorite. There you go.
Intelligence...
somewhere out there. Yeah.